[Music]
Hi everybody.
Welcome back, welcome back.
Welcome back.
It’s good to see you again.
Welcome to this second day.
It’s worth continuing this
adventure.
If we're gonna get through it, it's
gonna be together.
So let's keep going.
Hello!
We are happy that you’re back.
And we hope that you had a good conversation
with your group after the film last time.
And that you were able to share
how it all landed with you.
And yes I imagine that you’re each joining this
second episode in your very own way.
Some of you might still be processing
or feel shock or anger.
Or maybe you can’t wait to, you know, roll
up your sleeves and do something.
It’s like getting tumbled in the ocean,
just getting cycled into fear and despair
and being paralyzed.
Climate anxiety couldn’t be more
well-founded and so the first step is just to say…
you're, you’re not crazy.
This is like a very adaptive and normal response
to a totally unprecedented threat.
We just want to say: welcome to whatever
energy you bring to today’s episode.
There is no good or bad way to go about this.
And the format for today is the same.
So we’ll start with this one-hour film,
and then we'll set up a conversation
for your group for something like
30 minutes or, or more if you can.
And today we are at the bottom of the “U”
and we'll explore this question "Is there hope?"
[Music]
My hope is that we can save as much as possible.
I don't think there's any preventing
some of the effects of climate change.
But let's save what we can.
I really hope that we wake up.
I hope we, I hope we
don't wait till it's too late.
Today, I am well aware of what is going on.
I can see it, it's right in front of me.
I have two options:
The first one is to see everything and sink
and the second option,
is to have energy
and to be optimistic.
My nature is not to choose the first option.
You have to look for hope, and I think it's
less about you willingly looking, but kinda
forcefully making yourself look at those
moments of hope, so that you don't get lost in the
sort of depressing nature of it all.
When it comes to hope,
it’s tempting to look for quick fixes.
You know like renewable
energy or electric cars for instance.
But if we really want to answer
the big question of “Is there hope?”
we need to dig a little deeper.
We need first to understand how we got here.
Because the real puzzle is this, right: experts
have warned us for more than 50 years about
all this stuff that we talked about right-
the relentless destruction of living systems
and the pollution and the warming.
And heck, like 30 years ago, you know, political
leaders came together at the United Nations
and signed a treaty to "combat dangerous
human interference with the climate systems".
If only we had started
to act then, but instead of it,
things have just gotten worse and worse.
So we feel that we first need to
understand how come that we're so stuck,
you know, digging our own hole.
And only after that, we'll look
into the question of how can we change course.
So I hope you're ready because
here we go with episode two.
We'll start with the question.
How come we keep digging the hole we are in?
So why don’t we do what we know needs to
be done, you know, the things scientists have
told us for ages we need to do?
In our research, we learn something fascinating.
It turns out that what we set our minds to,
what we think is possible or impossible,
doesn't depend primarily on the
solutions we have or don't have.
It depends on something deeper on the
stories, the deep stories that shape our thinking.
Every group in history, every civilization
has a number of deep stories that shapes it.
Collective stories that tell people
what to strive for, what a good
life is and, and how the world works.
Not so long ago, people in Europe and colonial
America took for granted that they were part
of a feudal system with a king at the top.
And when the King dies, however smart
or inept his first-born son happens to be,
he gets to rule us all.
People thought: this is how the
world works and will always work.
Today, obviously, the idea seems quite ludicrous.
Because at some point, and really,
quite quickly,in the late 18th century the story changed.
Historians can argue endlessly about
“why” it suddenly changed, but the fact is:
hundreds of thousands of people
stopped believing in the old story of feudalism.
And embraced a new story.
They wrote pamphlets, talked in
the streets,and fought for democracy.
In just a few decades, the story of
self-rule became the dominant story.
Of course, democracy at first
included only land-owning white men.
It took a similar shift of stories to finally
end slavery and racial segregation in the
US, and that work is still very much ongoing.
In the same vein, until just a
century ago, women weren't allowed to vote,
and everyone took that for granted.
A deep, collective story held
that women were inferior to men,
and were not meant to have a public voice.
A group of women rallied
to challenge that idea.
It not only got women the right to vote, but
opened the doors to universities and the workplace.
And all the other places
they used to be excluded from.
This is how societies
make profound leaps forward.
We often get this wrong.
We focus on our presidents and
prime ministers and business leaders.
They have the power to fix things, right?
Well, they do, but just like all of us, what
they believe is possible is shaped by the
deep stories that dominate our thinking.
Update that story, and laws
and institutions often quickly follow.
I want to highlight this fascinating fact.
Profound change can happen quite quickly.
But up until the moment it happens,
it often feels like nothing is moving,
like nothing can beat the old story.
But if you look under
the surface, that’s not true.
Seeds are being planted.
And more and more people are
leaving the old story for a better one.
And then, when this reaches a critical mass,
like things suddenly shift much faster than
anyone could have predicted.
Sometimes in just a few years.
And this is what gives me hope, you know,
for the three crises we talked about last time.
More and more of us all over the world
are working hard to bring about a better story.
And right now things feel pretty stuck.
But who knows how close
we could be to a tipping point
where suddenly things change really fast.
I don't know, but I like to try and feel
that like, can you imagine if we
were at that stage where
suddenly things start to tip?
Before we imagine a better future, let’s
take the time we need to really understand
the deep story that got us where we are.
And it’s a story that tells us that:
“More is always better”.
Like we always need to pursue more
because more will make us happy and safe.
Some call it the “Story of More”.
And at some point, we realized that this story
has seeped into every system that shapes our
lives – that’s, you know, what deep stories do.
Maybe you've noticed this too, right.
The Story of More shapes how we produce food,
what we consume, how we produce energy,
how we run our education systems, …
In all of these places, we strive
for more, and more, and more.
And at first, it makes sense…
until we reach a point where instead of
bringing more happiness and more prosperity…
it brings more loneliness and more destruction.
Today we'll look at 3 of these systems - those
that are responsible for most of the destruction
we talked about in episode 1.
So, first we’ll look at Food, then
Consumption and Production, and finally Energy.
And for each of them, we'll first
look at the old Story, the Story of More.
So yeah, unfortunately, we'll
dwell a little bit more on the ugly stuff.
But then, for all 3 topics, we'll also
look at a better story that is emerging.
So, let’s start with our food system.
Why food?
What does it have to do with climate
change, or mass extinction or pollution?
Well it turns out a lot, right!
The way we produce food and transport it
and waste so much of it along the way,
is a key driver of pollution and
the collapse of the living planet.
And it produces 30% of all
the gas that warms our planet.
Let’s just look at how eggs are produced.
It used to be pretty straightforward.
Every farmer used to have a few chickens in
their backyard that would eat bugs and food
scraps and then lay eggs.
Farmers knew their personalities.
Just like humans, chickens form complex hierarchies.
Some chickens are shy, some are
aggressive and some are curious.
But then, the Story of More took over.
An accountant who owned some chickens
had the idea to put them in vertical cages,
so you can concentrate
more chickens per square foot.
That idea naturally led to cram more and
more chickens in each cage to maximize profit.
Farmers were forced to play
along or they would be left behind.
You could simply no longer
compete if you let your chickens run free.
The trouble is: when chickens are confined
like this, in a way that nature never intended,
they go mad and attack each other.
An extra step was added to make this work
and keep the chickens from killing each other:
the beaks of chicks are clipped or
burned off in a machine, with no anesthesia.
Imagine how you would feel if you had to do
this job for 8 hours a day, burning off the
beaks of thousands of chicks!
Now, chickens can go mad
without killing each other.
Which means you can stuff millions
of hens into gigantic egg factories.
But that brings up another problem.
When millions of animals are crammed
in a way that doesn’t happen in nature,
infectious diseases evolve that
kill  off whole flocks, again and again.
So all the chickens need to
be put on antibiotics, all the time.
Without constant antibiotics,
the factory system would collapse.
But far from being a solution,
this creates two new big problems.
Two ticking time bombs.
For one, millions of animals sitting in their
own waste is the perfect breeding ground
to grow deadly viruses.
Experts warn us that if you want to
create a deadly, global pandemic for humans,
just build factory farms.
The second thing they worry about
is the massive overuse of antibiotics -
the same antibiotics we humans use.
It’ll breed bacteria that
become resistant to these antibiotics.
And when that happens…
well, surgery and childbirth will
gradually become a potentially fatal risk again,
as it used to be.
Chemotherapy will no longer be safely practiced.
Infectious diseases we have
forgotten will return to be deadly threats.
That’s the Story of More.
Every step has some logic to it, but it
ends up creating a Frankenstein system.
Eggs are just one example, but the
story of factory farming is similar for turkeys,
pigs, and cows.
And to feed all these animals with soy
and grain, the pressure is relentless to take
over more precious ecosystems.
We get 18% of our energy
intake from meat and dairy.
But it’s not 18% of the world’s
farmland that we use for meat and dairy.
It’s… 83%.
And that’s why we keep burning more
of the Amazon rainforest, bringing it closer to collapse.
One thing we really, really ask you to do is:
don’t blame farmers for this absurd system!
Yeah.
Farmers feed us and the farmers
I know work harder than anyone else.
Like they never get a day off, right?
They're often the first one to suffer from
the system that they haven't chosen or even
designed, right.
In this system all of the profits get sucked
up out of the farms and farming communities
into a few giant meat companies.
And every year thousands of small farms,
you know, give up, crushed, you know by debts
and by these giant factory farms.
And it's a terrible deal
for us taxpayers too, right.
Most of us don't realize, but we prop up
these gigantic factory farms
with millions of dollars, pounds and euros
of subsidies creating an uneven playing field
that make it hard for smaller family farms.
The whole factory meat industry has become
so ugly that we’re not even allowed to see it.
Did you know that in the US, meat lobbyists
convinced legislators in many states to make
it a “terrorist” offense to
film inside factory farms?
No one is allowed to inform the
public about what’s going on inside!
So over and over again, we’re led
to believe that the food we eat is this
when really it’s this.
And I hate that we have so little choice.
Think about what you had to eat today,
you know... for breakfast or for lunch.
I don't know, can you remember what it was?
It's almost certain that if you had meat,
egg or dairy, it came from a factory farm, right.
Even though it's entirely possible, as we'll
see, to raise animals in a different way that
heals rather than destroys the planet,
but you're almost never given that option.
And it’s not just meat.
It’s the bread, the fruits
and vegetables we eat too.
When chemical firms discovered they could
transform petroleum into cheap pesticides
At first, it looked really promising.
But now we wake up and see how vibrant ecosystems
have vanished at the hands of massive monocultures
and pesticides.
Fertilizer runoff pollutes rivers
and lakes we can no longer swim in.
Food is massively wasted
before it even gets to the supermarket.
And lots of farm hands are exploited.
And we eat products full of pesticides that
might give us cancer and other diseases.
My childhood farm, where I grew up in
central Illinois, um, we really, really wanted to
be good stewards of the land…
The trouble, you know with that...
It turns out that the use of herbicides has
lots of short-term and long-term consequences...
My father, you know, he was, you know, a chemical
applicator just on our farm...He was diagnosed
with Parkinson's at 46.
46 years old is fairly young
to come down with Parkinson's.
In the Story of More, we optimize
one thing at the expense of everything else.
We isolate one breed of chicken or one plant
on thousands of acres, and squeeze every drop
of productivity out of it.
But everything around it dies.
It’s the same with profits: family farms
and local communities who do the hard work
are suffering or closing down.
All the profits go to a handful of
large traders and big agriculture firms.
It's another system gone mad.
If we start measuring right now by the
amount of farmers that we are losing every year,
you know, the system is
already started to disintegrate.
Like we can be incredibly clever and we can
come up with these really complicated systems
and mass food production.
But if it's on the wrong target, because it's
going to eventually come back and bite us
in the butt.
This factory farm industrial model isn't going
to work in the long term...there's gonna be
a point in which the
systems are going to fail.
Why are we sharing all this?
It’s not that we like this disturbing stuff.
But we really need the courage to understand
the Story of More if we want to get to a better one.
And I don't know about you, but I know that I
often just wanna shrug this all off and just say
like, hey, yeah, you know this is normal.
It's not easy for me to actually stand still
and accept and admit that I live in, and that
I participate in, in, in these larger Frankenstein
systems that have become deeply destructive
and absurd.
Okay...it’s time to move on to our
second example: Consumption and Production.
In our Western part of the world
the value of someone's life,
and what makes a good life
is often measured by our possessions.
Whether it is a nice
car or a great house or
the fancy vacation you have.
It’s only with this whole philosophy of
infinite growth paradigm that we come out
with this foolishness that we have now.
The Story of More tells us
that we are what we own.
That if something doesn’t feel right, or
if we’re unhappy, we just need something
more to make us happy again.
Now we all know that these
things don't make us happier.
But it’s pounded into our brains every
day with billions of dollars of advertising.
How did we get here?
A hundred years ago, a new generation was
growing up in the Western World whose basic
needs were finally being met.
We could have celebrated that we were now
free to focus on what really makes life meaningful.
But we went down a different path.
In 1929, a commission established by President
Hoover – the “Committee on Recent Economic Change"
came up with a clear vision.
Advertising can “develop national
consumption habits” and create "new wants, which will
make way for endlessly newer
wants as fast as they're satisfied”.
In the decades that followed, advertising
techniques have become very sophisticated.
The key driver of modern advertising is to
start with making us feel bad about ourselves.
That’s why models in advertising are
photoshopped to be impossibly thin and good-looking,
and live in houses that most
of us will never be able to afford.
Unconsciously, we are made to feel insufficient.
Only to be suggested that… if we
would only buy this, we’d be better off,
we’d finally be happy and whole.
And the trick gets repeated again and again.
Once a person enters professional life,
they have freedom, they can
take a vacation whenever they want
Some people also want to
climb the social ladder
with a nice purse, with a beautiful suit,
beautiful things etc.
Then at some point, little by little,
after going to very good restaurants,
and taking beautiful vacations,
I began to realize something vicious
Because I work so much;
I am trying to make up for it with
outings, trips, restaurants,
objects, purchases...
But in fact, that doesn't make up for it.
It sort of feels like a big waste.
Why are we all wearing blinders
in this rat race to nowhere.
that doesn't make anyone happy?
Consumption is another system gone crazy –
not only are we made unhappy so we buy things
we don’t really need, but we
are pushed into debt to do it.
We work ever longer hours to make ends meet,
come home so exhausted, we collapse in front
of the TV.
Compared to our parents and grandparent’s
generation, we have far less time to hang
out with friends and
become involved in our community.
For many of us, the Story of More
has really become a story of loneliness.
Our grandparents used to be deeply embedded
in their community - through volunteering,
church groups, unions, dancing at the fair,
community sports, or hanging out in public
spaces.
Much of that has disappeared.
Who I talk to, my patients and my
community, people are generally not very happy.
And I think people feel very lonely and, what
they can buy or flying here for the weekend,
the kind of the heavy impact
consumer role, It doesn't lead to happiness.
Studies show that today, loneliness
kills more than cigarettes or heart disease.
And I’m sure you can think, you know, of at
least one person that you love that is struggling with
loneliness or depression or addiction.
And they’re not the only ones.
It turns out, 50% of Americans
say no one knows them well
and 35% say they are chronically lonely.
In Europe, 75 million people are so isolated,
they never see a friend or a family member,
or they do so once a month at most.
I remember reading an article that
made a deep impression on me years ago.
Nurses in a terminal care unit of a hospital
listed the major regrets of people about to die.
And here’s the top 3:
I wish I'd had the courage to live a life
true to myself, not the life others expected of me.
I wish I hadn't worked so hard, and
had spent more time with the people I love.
And I wish I'd had the
courage to express my feelings.
And it stopped me in my tracks.
Because at the time, I was working way too
much, you know, I had little time for friends,
I was chasing the next promotion
and a bigger paycheck.
And according to the Story of More
everything was right on track, right.
Except it wasn't, right?
It turns out it robbed me of 10 years of my life.
Like they just flew by and I can
barely remember them because I worked so much.
And it wasn't a conscious choice I made.
It's just that, you know, already growing
up that Story of More was everywhere
around me.
And this message is even
more relentless for kids today.
To be happy and worth something,
you need to have the newest toys, wear the coolest
brands.
You need more followers, more likes.
There are countless studies that show
that the current generation of teens today is the
most anxious and depressed ever.
This mad consumption system requires
an equally destructive production system to sustain it.
We have to dig up ever more metals
and transform ever more petroleum into plastic.
Transform it in faraway factories.
Ship it around the world, for the
whole thing to end up in landfills just a bit later.
Dig it, make it, trash it, that’s the
essence of today's production system.
And when you think about it, it’s astonishing
how many resources go into something that
is meant to be used just once,
thrown away and never used again.
Take a plastic spoon for instance.
It's somehow easier to pump oil out
of the ground, ship it across the world, turn it
into a plastic shape, wrap it in more plastic,
ship it across the world again, use tons of
gas to deliver it to millions of shop,
than it is to simply wash a spoon?
We are really hitting a wall.
And obviously it’s the same
with our last example - Energy.
When it comes to energy, we all
pretty much know what the old story is.
For a long time, we had to rely on oil, gas
and coal – the primary energy sources on
which our modern lives are built.
Fossil fuels have made so much possible -
so in many ways, we can be grateful for what
this has done for us.
But here too, we are
reaching the end of a story.
Once it was easy to find oil and gas.
But because we need ever more of it,
now we have to dig deeper and deeper to find it,
and take more and more risks.
And move towards dirtier and dirtier sources.
Too often we get massive spills where we
extract it, and we get spills when we transport it.
We deploy our military all around the world
to secure the supply we depend upon, and pay
billions to dictators we’d
otherwise never pander to.
And then, of course, there is the issue
that burning fossil fuels is the main driver of
climate change, or as
some now call it - global scorching.
We must leave the fossil fuels we have in
the ground, or we’ll trigger the booby traps
we talked about on day 1.
This can sound like big
geo-political stuff that has nothing to do with me.
But we’re all trapped in that system.
And everytime I plug in my phone,
or switch on lights in the house or put gas in the car,
I’m forced to participate in a bit
more destruction, pollution and warming.
Even though I don’t want to.
So we've looked at three examples and
it's pretty clear that the story of more however
successful it was for a
while is no longer serving us.
We need something better.
Well, here is the hopeful part.
If we know where to look, we can see
a new story emerging, in all sorts of fields and
all sorts of places.
A better story.
And it’s only the beginning, but in that
story is a powerful seed that could help us
overcome the enormous crisis we’re facing.
So what does a better story look like?
Let’s go back to food.
[Birds singing]
Look how much he likes to have his back rubbed.
I think he likes me better.
I think he does too,
he always likes girls better.
Yeah, that’s right, cause girls are better.
My name is Holly Arbuckle and John
and I are the co-founders of Singing Pastures.
And that's our farm.
Where we raise pasture-raised non GMO pigs
and we sell food from our farm and other farms
around the country.
The kind of farming that Holly and
John practice is called regenerative farming.
It’s both ancient and its
principles as well as being cutting edge.
Our form of farming is, you know,
biomimicry, it’s farming in nature’s image.
Nature has a plan
that works really really well.
Every grassland on earth co-evolved
under the evolutionary pressure of a large group
of grazing herbivores.
So, we’re gonna replicate what the bison
were doing here, what the wilderbeast do in the serengeti,
what the caribou doin the far north.
We are gonna keep the animals
relatively tightly bunched and continuously moving.
We think of ourselves as grass farmers,
as carbon farmers, we think of ourselves and
our livestock as
instruments that are healing ecosystems.
You know, I see fields that used to be bare,
cracked soil and sparsely populated with thorn bushes.
And now they're growing, you know,
12 species of forage and they are lush and they look
like Ireland.
See, this is exactly what we want.
All the soil particles literally look
like you are looking at chocolate cake.
Look at all the roots going through it.
Regenerative farming replaces all the
expensive pesticides and fertilizers with natural principles.
And not having to buy those
means more profits stay on the farm.
I got into the world of regenerative
agriculture ...It was a profit question.
You know, we were noticing that our farm
didn't make enough money…Sometimes I wish they
just didn't call it regenerative farming.
I just wished they called it, you know, a
profitable, sustainable farming or something,
you know, because I think that we would
attract more of the people we want to attract.
Our costs go down,
our production increases, the animals are happier.
The animals require less pharmaceuticals.
We have low cost, simple, effective
solutions that could quickly build soil which is gonna
sequester carbon, it’s gonna
mitigate the risk of both flooding and drought, it
makes the food more nutritious,
it helps restore healthy water cycles.
And we can do it.
And we can do it right away.
In a farm that uses advanced regenerative
practices, like John and Holly’s, life bounces
back - songbirds and wildlife return.
And through photosynthesis, crops and
lush grasslands absorb tons of carbon from the
atmosphere and store it in the topsoil
they recreate - 2 to 5 tons per hectare or more,
every year.
This is a picture of
typical land in industrial agriculture.
And here is what it looks like, 10 years later,
when a farm took part of the land and switched
over to regenerative agriculture.
We’ll soon need to feed 10 billion
people and big agriculture firms tell us we need
chemicals to do that.
Well there are many studies that show us that
we don’t.
We can grow as much food per acre or
more when we work with natural patterns rather
than against them.
My primary motivation is to
improve the lives of farmers and the earth.
I want farmers to be able to
grow more food and have better profits.
...and healing ecosystems
because I feel intimately connected
to the land that I produce food on.
Regenerative farms, like John and Holly’s,
are starting to spread - just in the US, there
are more and more, and
it’s the same in Europe and beyond.
Now we need to dream bigger!
Say to scale it up to a whole region, like
in France, in the Drôme valley, where one
third of farmers are already organic.
Or to a whole city like Liège, where my
family is from, that developed a vision to get all
of its food from local and sustainable farmers.
And link those farmers to local shops
and bakers and of course - this is Belgium,
you know - to local brewers!
It’s early days, but it’s with this kind
of vision that we can eventually shift a whole
food system.
And then to go even further, you know to
speed up this transition to regenerative farming
on a large scale.
We need governments to stop the wasteful
subsidies that keep industrial and factory farming going.
If we stop that, and instead,
support regenerative agriculture,
this system could tip and
it could actually tip quite fast!
Farmers will be the heroes
that help us cool down our planet.
You’ll swim in rivers and lakes again, everywhere.
And no one will have to breathe in
pesticides or cut the beaks of chicks for 8 hours a day.
Family farms can make a living again.
That's what 2050 could look like, for all
of us, if we radically turn the tide now.
And I don’t know about you,
but that’s the 2050 I want to be a part of.
We can actually make the world
cooler again, more beautiful again.
Wildlife and ecosystems could flourish
and our food system can become more stable.
These are images from the Loess plateau
in China, a region the size of the Netherlands.
Overgrazing had turned the region into a desert.
In the 1990s, local authorities
embarked on a major program to revive it.
People created terraces to store rainwater,
they planted trees which also retain water…
Within ten years, life exploded.
7 rivers have come back to life.
The economy bounced back too,
providing livelihoods for thousands of people.
I can't help myself, like I, I just love to
go back and forth on these images.
You know, back and forth, back and forth…
like it’s...it's just amazing!
Life can bounce back at breakneck speed.
Empty oceans find abundant life
again if we allow them to recover.
Even in the city you can regenerate life.
Or in your front yard.
We could even return land to wilderness.
As we mentioned earlier, most of the
world’s farmland is tied up to meat and dairy.
And Today, 40% of food in the world is wasted.
That’s 40% of all farmland going to waste.
So if we reduce food waste and if we get
more proteins from plants and from plant-based
meat and dairy, we could free up so much land.
Not only could we feed everyone, but we
could return huge tracts of less productive land
to nature and let them go wild again!
So that’s the better
story when it comes to Food.
A new story is also emerging for consumption
and production, the other topic we talked about.
Well, in many ways, this new story is full
of common sense and wisdom from the past.
It tells us something
we all know deep down inside.
What really makes us happy
and safe is not the stuff we buy.
It’s our relationship, our friendships,
the community we feel a part of,
the meaning we find in what we do.
For millions of years, people have lived
in harmony with the planet, you know, we understood
not to take too much and
to give back and to take care of.
That doesn't mean you have to give up all
of your possessions or do a Marie Kondo and
become a minimalist and give everything up.
I think it's more about respecting yourself,
​​respecting your bank account and your
work, and respecting the earth
and the people who made your things.
Um, the systems
who brought your things to you.
The more I get involved in working with
my community towards our collective interest.
It's much more fulfilling than what I could
buy...There's studies about the pleasure that
comes out of spending time
with people... versus buying something.
Buying something,
it doesn't boost your level of happiness.
But being more connected to a community does.
[singing]
This is Barcelona, in Spain.
Much of the city has a grid design.
In some areas, they’ve created “super
blocks” of 9 blocks where cars can drive
on the outside, but inside,
the streets are for people, not cars.
Inside the block, kids can play safely.
People exercise, meet friends, dance.
Vegetable and flower gardens take over.
You know what people love more than anything?
The humble picnic bench!
Put a few picnic benches out,
and people organize birthday parties.
People come out, sit down and talk.
At first, some residents opposed the idea
of the superblocks, as happens with any change.
But just a year later, it’s such an
overwhelming success, no one wants to go back.
Give us a space to meet and hang out and step
off the treadmill of working, consuming, working,
consuming and we take it!
The plan in Barcelona is to create 500 superblocks,
it will profoundly change the city for the better.
I love that story!
Not that super blocks are going to be
enough to save us, but the fact that we’re using
space to support connection
and community that is huge.
And suddenly, we have a space where we're
not expected to be either consumers or workers.
There's a space to just be.
And in the same vein,
there's a story we love from Switzerland.
Two young designer had the simple idea.
They created sheets of stickers with
logos of items that you might be willing to lend
to a neighbor.
Think about it, right.
Are there things that you own
that you would be okay to lend to someone?
Perhaps a drill or a ladder
or a waffle maker or a camping tent?
I don't know if you've pictured a few things,
but now imagine you put the corresponding
stickers on your mailbox.
And you invite people in your
apartment block or in your street to do the same.
If they want to, with the item that they own.
Now, every time you enter your building or
walk along your street, you'll see all the things
you have access to, for free.
And it also builds community, the very thing
that has been proven to make us happier in life!
You know, that to me is like the better story.
We can relax.
We spend less money and yet we have
access to what we need when we need it.
In the same spirit, more and more local
communities have tool libraries and toy libraries.
Why would libraries be only for books?
We have actually a repair cafe where people
who know how to fix things come, and people
have broken things come, and
then you fix it or they fix it and you like watch.
Repair cafés are popping up everywhere –
in schools, in community centers,
and in church basements - places where passionate fixers
help you repair stuff for free,
because they love doing it.
It is way more fun than just buying
something new. You know, you're connected to
this, you know, kid who goes to college
and you like, see that he can fix it and,
you know, there's lots
of people who have different skills,
Repair cafés, just like second hand shops,
toy and tool libraries help us get away from
the old linear system of
“dig it, make it, trash it”.
Instead, we move to a circular system
where we start with reducing what we produce and
manufacture to only what is really needed.
And then we share it, reuse it
and repair it over and over.
And only when that’s no longer
possible, do we recycle it.
And we do all of that without pollution and
without fossil fuels that overheat the planet.
That’s the new story of consumption!
But what about manufacturing and mass production?
Is it possible to have
a better story there, too?
I mean at a really large scale?
Well, yes, Ray Anderson, a businessman
from Georgia is a great example of this.
Ray founded a company called Interface in
1973 and grew it into the largest carpet manufacturer
in the world.
You know those 20-inch
carpet tiles you see in offices everywhere?
That’s Interface.
I was not an environmentalist.
I hadn't given I had never given a thought
to what we were taking from the earth or doing
to the earth to make our products.
But when I found Hawkins book it was a
spear in the chest and I read it and wept because
it just laid out so clearly the problems
of the industrial system, the system of which
my company, my creation,
this third child of mine, was an integral part.
At the time, Ray Anderson was 60.
He realized that his business relied
on extracting 1.2 billion pounds of raw materials a year -
most of it oil and natural gas that become
plastic fibers - to produce and ship millions of square
yards of carpets to clients who,
a decade later, inevitably trash them in landfills.
He set himself a goal, that in the
Story of More, would sound crazy:
To bring the production process into a “closed loop” –
no longer taking anything
from the earth but only recycle existing material.
And to do that without polluting in any way.
It unleashed a whole wave of innovations.
They redesigned their products and their machines.
They began leasing their
carpets, instead of selling them.
So that when the time comes to replace
the carpet, they can recuperate the tiles and
recycle all of the materials.
They switched the entire
production process to solar power.
Sadly, Anderson died a few years ago.
But today, his company is well and
on its way to meet his crazy goal: Shifting from
a linear to a circular, closed-loop production,
something that at first was unimaginable.
Interface is still the global
market leader, and they are highly profitable.
And as you can imagine,
their workforce is incredibly proud to work there.
Interface is now setting itself its
next big goal - not just to be carbon neutral, but
to become “carbon negative”.
You know, remember how with regenerative
farming, plants, you know, can draw down carbon from
the atmosphere and store it in the ground?
Well, with plant-based fibers, you know,
Interface is starting to store that carbon in the carpets.
And Ray was ahead of his time.
He happened to be in carpets,
but really any company can choose to do this.
Imagine your workplace doing something similar.
Like I don't know for you but
I would feel so motivated and so energized.
And wow so proud!
So that’s production and consumption.
And to round this out let’s talk about
the new story of energy.
Decades of technological innovation
have made wind and solar so cheap that in many places
it’s now cheaper than coal,
oil and gas and will soon be much cheaper.
Even without climate change, we would still
be moving away from fossil fuels simply because
we have better, cleaner technology now.
Electric cars are about to get much
cheaper, than traditional cars too and they are much
more fun to drive.
Of course, the stuff that goes into wind and
solar panels and electric cars still has to be dug
from the ground, like oil and gas
- so it’s not perfect.
But it’s still key to stop warming
the planet and give us a liveable future.
It’s also important to remember that
renewable energy is just a technology, not a silver bullet.
There’s a risk we fall into the old story
- create ever more demand to make ever more
profits, and destroy
ecosystems along the way.
We need to be efficient about the resources
we use, and not simply go crazy digging up
all the lithium in the
world just because we can.
Let’s only put up the solar panels
and wind turbines we need, not more.
And let’s use them to benefit our communities.
Because with renewables, we can produce
energy on our roofs, store it in batteries, and create
micro-grids with the neighbors.
The money stays in the local
economy, and we become more self-reliant.
Oil and gas created good jobs for many years,
but renewables will create a whole lot more of them!
Already now, solar panel installer and wind
turbine technician are among the fastest growing
job categories.
And we’ll need plenty of people to install
batteries, heat pumps, and car charging stations.
We’ll see lots of work return to
local communities that had been bleeding jobs.
Let’s zoom out.
Everywhere, in food, in consumption,
production energy and other areas too, a new story,
a better story is emerging and gaining steam.
And sometimes rapidly.
But the million dollar question is:
can this be enough?
Let’s assume we do all this,
can we turn the ship around?
In 2014, a group of 200 scientists and
specialists put together a list of all the big ideas on
how to stop climate breakdown.
They mainly focused on carbon,
but many of their solutions also provide breakthroughs
in stabilizing ecosystems and reducing pollution.
This effort is called "Project Drawdown".
They came up with a list of 80 items -
with things we’ve talked about like upgrading
the way we grow food, replanting
forests, and switching to renewable energy.
But also other things,
some of them quite surprising.
For example recycling greenhouse gasses
in air conditioning units, which turns out to
be a big deal.
They asked the question: What happens
if we were to take all our existing solutions and
scale them up… would this be
enough to stop the world from getting too warm?
Or do we fall short? The answer is…
Yes, it could be enough, if we manage
to implement all the major solutions we have at hand.
Actually, once we get to a point where we
stop the warming, in principle, we could even
go into reverse.
We could draw carbon back down from the
atmosphere and turn the thermostat back down.
That’s why they called their research “Drawdown”.
If you're interested in more,
you can check out the book they published about it.
The other question they asked is,
how much is all of this going to cost?
The answer is quite astonishing: yes,
at first we’ll have to invest a lot, but within 30
years it will pay back
three times what it costs.
In fact, and this blows my mind.
Like we can pay for all of the investments
to get to a hundred percent renewable energy
just from the saving on healthcare,
because we won't have all of the diseases from air
pollution anymore.
And if you're interested, you can
read up on all this research with the links we've
put on online on The Week's website.
When I first started learning about this,
I thought that the goal was to do less harm
and stop destroying our planet.
But now I understand that we can be
much more ambitious: we can go into reverse and heal
a lot of the damage we’ve done.
And that to me, is so much more motivating.
So if we start to invest massively
like really seriously right now, like now, now.
Then we'll see some of the
benefits right away, like cleaner air.
And there could be a big, big sigh of relief
by 2050, because we'll have passed the danger
zone and start to draw down.
So from a purely technical
perspective, it could be done.
But let's face it, like it will
take tremendous energy and determination.
We have to implement something like
80 solutions, you know, at the same time on a huge scale,
worldwide.
And for those of us who live in the big
economies, like the US and Europe and China, like
we must lead the way like this is a
massive effort that will require absolute dedication.
And I sometimes I wonder
if we have this in us to do something of this scale.
But then we learnt that in the past, we’ve
been able to pull off some impressive infrastructure
upgrades, and we’ve
done it more than a few times.
So if we’ve been able to do it before, it
would be unconscionable not to try it now.
In the 19th century, when cities
became more and more crowded,
diseases like cholera swept through them.
It killed thousands and thousands of people.
When a doctor figured out
it was coming from human waste, every…
single… street in London, in NY, in every
city was cut open to install the gigantic
sewer system we still use today.
This would be a huge endeavor in our time.
Imagine what it was then, all by hand,
long before mechanical excavators!
Or take this example:
This is a street in New York in 1904.
You know what urbanists’
biggest headache was back then?
Horse poop.
There were places in New York where
manure was piled up 20 feet high, that’s 6 meters!
Expert commissions made
grand  plans to deal with the issue.
And then this happened.
This is New York just 9 years later.
The same happened with electricity.
In Europe and the US, we electrified
our cities and then, in just a decade or two,
the whole continent.
We are capable of amazing transformations.
During World War II, the US
achieved incredible feats even faster.
Just 2 years after Pearl Harbor,
the US was producing a plane every 4 minutes.
And two military ships every day.
The whole economy was rewired,
new technologies were developed.
This set the basis for the
post-war middle-class boom.
We are capable of almost
unbelievable things, when we put our minds to it.
We’ve done it before.
More recently, China, in record time, built
an extraordinary network of high-speed trains.
23.000 miles or 37,000 km,
in just 12 years, that connect all the major cities.
It connected the country in a whole new way.
In other words, like we could do this,
you know, if we decide collectively to do so.
And, my god, it will be worth it!
You know,, for years and years, we’ve
been told that in order to “save the planet”,
we'll have to sacrifice.
Like the good days are over.
Well… more and more,
we feel it might be just the opposite.
Our lives can actually become richer with
a better food system, and stronger communities,
and a healthier energy system.
There's a sense that in order to end the climate
crisis, we have to live in huts with no electricity
[laughing] and eat spinach for dinner.
I think that's what people think it is, but
actually I think climate action is a chance
to completely upscale or make everything better.
Sure.
You know, the transition will certainly be
super difficult at times, but when was that
ever reason to shy away from a challenge?
Because ultimately we have
more to gain than to lose, right?
For us, that was sort of a major shift,
in our thinking.you know, even
if these crisis magically disappeared, you
know, we'd still want to do all of those things
that we talked about because
they will make our lives so much better.
Reorienting around a sustainable society
could make people happier
than they've been in my generation.
So I do hope it's time
for a new, a new human story.
That's less about domination and
extraction and more about cooperation and sharing.
It’s people doing farming, you know it’s
people growing things, it’s people going
back into arts and doing all these other things.
It’s beautiful, it’s like a really
a renaissance happening right here in the
middle of chaos.
And it’s beautiful.
You know, with all the superhero movies
in our culture, we’ve sort of bought the idea
that it takes a chosen
one with super powers to save us.
So we wait for someone
our political leaders to do something.
But in real life, that’s not
how profound change ever came about.
In real life, it happens when
we reach a critical mass and then things shift.
That’s almost mathematical.
And that’s the part I find exciting!
Because it means I am needed, that you are
needed and that we can all contribute something.
So if what excites you is innovation,
well that’s awesome because we need that!
And if you are into recreating
communities and a society that’s more fair, well again
perfect because we need that too.
Or if you are into common sense and
what’s good about traditional ways, we need that
as well so that we shape a
better future with the best of the past.
You know, when you look back at history,
some generations get thrown an incredible challenge.
Freedom and self rule after thousands of
years of monarchy, ending slavery and legal segregation,
women gaining the right to vote, defeating
fascism in Europe, bringing down communist
dictatorships.
Well, for all of us alive today,
this is our challenge, our adventure.
We must upgrade our energy systems
and our agricultural industrial systems.
We must protect them and
expand the remaining wild ecosystems.
And we must do all this at once.
Like it’s World War II mobilization on steroids.
Yes, and sometimes it looks like things
are not moving nearly fast enough, and we feel
depressed.
But then I remember, it felt just as impossible
to people in the past before a massive shift
happened.
It always does.
But just imagine we make
this happen, the energy we’ll feel.
I know that I want to roll up my sleeves.
I have to be part of this.
And how this will play out
exactly, no one knows yet.
In our group, some of us are excited about
the role of new technologies, while others
are more excited about social
movements or simplifying their lives.
Some of us believe that to make this transition,
governments must step up big times, but others
think that personal
responsibility will be key.
And in your own group, you might also have
different perspectives on some of these topics.
And that's OK!
That’s probably even a good thing,
because we need to come at this from all angles.
And we started this
episode with the question: Is there hope?
And our situation reminds
me of a friend of mine, you know,
who was told that she had cancer.
And I remembered that at first she just
kept asking her doctor, you know: "Please tell me,
will I make it?"
Yeah.
And then she realized like, whatever
the doctor would say, it wouldn't ultimately
matter because she was gonna
do whatever it would take, regardless.
This was now her fight, you know, her adventure.
And i’m glad to say she survived.
What we learned from her is that,
in the end, it’s not about hope from the outside –
say a doctor or a climate expert.
It’s about the fire we have in our belly.
And that's what we'll talk about next time.
In the third and final time
together, we'll delve into the question,
what can I do? What can we do?
You know, what would give us joy?
You know, what would really
make us proud, but that's for day three.
Yeah.
Because now, it's time again for the
most important part – the conversation in your group
just like you did on day 1.
Because it's hard to
process a topic as mighty as this one alone.
So we need each
other to make sense of it all.
Yeah.
So we wish you a great conversation and we'll
see you in a minute to kick off that conversation.
Bye.