Hey everybody.
Welcome to
The Week.
1, 2, 3, clap.
Disaster.
Hello everyone,
welcome to The Week.
Hi and welcome to The Week.
Good morning, good afternoon, good evening.
Welcome to The Week.
Glad you're here.
My name is Frank Johnson.
My name is Ashley McClure.
John and Holly Arbuckle
at Singing Pastures Farm.
My name is Yancy,
and I'm really glad that you're here.
That is it, the first episode.
I really hope you
have a great experience.
I’m so excited that you’re settling in
and hope that you enjoy this conversation
that is really meaningful.
Put on your seatbelts,
because it's going to be a bumpy ride today.
1, 2, 3.
Perfect.
Welcome!
Yes. Welcome everyone!
Right now you might be at home
with your friends or your family,
or maybe you're at work with your colleagues.
And yeah, it's exciting for us
to picture you
wherever you are with your group.
And we're grateful
that you decided to join us.
My name is Helene.
And I’m Frederic.
And we’re married, we have two kids.
They are 8 and 11.
I’m French,
Fred is from Belgium
where we met years ago.
Hence our accents,
so please bear with us.
And we now live in the United States.
And three years ago,
we went through a profound shift.
Before that we, we sort of knew that
things are in a bad shape
when it comes to, you know,
the climate and the environment.
But it felt abstract.
Like it didn't really feel like
it had anything to do with our, our own lives.
And plus it felt pretty depressing.
So we kind of, you know, did our best
to tune it out and, and not engage with it.
And then one day
good friends of ours came to visit.
[Music]
And we were impressed by their courage
to really grapple with this.
And it made it real for us.
And so when they left, you know,
I remember we looked at each other
and we said like, you know:
If they have the courage to do this,
we should be able to do it too.
And so when they left,
we had this urge to learn everything we could.
We read and researched
and watched documentaries.
And along the way, we met amazing people
who also had been on a similar journey
to face this reality.
And for us facing this was a real shock.
Um, we went on what could best be described
like a U-shaped journey.
At first it brought up lots of, you know,
sadness and fear and anger.
But luckily we didn't get stuck there.
We came out on the other side
with lots of energy,
with lots of clarity about what was important
and what we wanted to do with our lives.
And after we went through this, uh,
we invited some of our friends
to go on a similar journey.
And you know, this was a pandemic.
So we did it on, on video calls.
Hi, I'm Helene.
Yeah, I'm Frederic.
And they liked it so much
that they invited
some of their friends and then their friends.
And it started to gather steam.
And at some point we figured
let's turn this into films,
make them free and,
and see what happens.
[Music grows louder]
And we met this wonderful film team.
And long story short,
here we are, together with you to do this.
And it’s not just us.
Every day, everywhere around the world,
thousands of people are coming to terms
with what’s happening.
And in this film, you’ll meet a few of them.
Nine people we fell in love with
and who said “yes” when we asked them
if they would share with us and with you
how they came to face this issue
and what they decided to do about it.
So there is Ashley.
A family doctor in California.
There is Ophélie, in France,
who works in construction.
There’s Frank, in Memphis Tennessee,
who fights the pollution
that has devastated his community.
Scarlett, a student and activist in England,
who saw the consequences
of climate change in Kashmir,
where her parents are from.
We have John and Holly,
9th generation farmers,
who made the leap
to regenerative agriculture.
And also Pauline, in Paris,
who rallied colleagues to make changes
from within her workplace.
Yancy, in Arizona,
an ex-Marine and grandfather
who left the oil industry
to work for an electric truck company.
And finally we have
Peter [English pronunciation]…
or Peter [German pronunciation].
A German lawyer who for 25 years has had
an impressive string of wins in court
to protect our future.
Some of them live in North America,
the others in Europe.
And we focused on these two continents
because we have no lived experience elsewhere.
So we didn’t feel quite qualified to talk
about Asia, South America or Africa.
That that being said, you know,
if you live outside of Europe or the US,
and you want to create a local version of
the week for where you live,
please reach out because
we'd love to help you make it happen.
So, Ashley, Frank, Pauline, Scarlett,
Peter, John, Holly,
Ophelie, Yancy, us…
We all are really different.
We're different in terms of our age,
our jobs, our politics.
Some of us are religious, others are not.
We're different in how much or little money
we’ve got left at the end of the month.
But we have one thing in common.
Each of us had the courage
to really look into
the environmental breakdown
that’s happening.
And then figured out
what we wanted to do about it.
And this is exactly what we are
inviting you to do with us now.
We’re going to meet three times
over the course of a week.
You know, that's why we called it The Week.
And each time we'll start with
a one hour film,
and then we'll invite you to have
a conversation with your group
for something like 30 to 45 minutes.
So, we'll go through the U together.
In episode one, we'll go down the rabbit hole
to really understand the situation we're in.
In episode two, we'll examine
how we got into this mess
and what it would take to get out of it.
And in episode three,
we'll look into the question
what can I do?
What can we do?
And there's one more person
that we want to introduce to you.
To share with you
everything we learned,
we looked for a narrator,
like they do in films,
somebody with a good voice.
And, and we figured,
instead of hiring some random actor
that we wouldn't know
that we'd ask our friend Seamus, you know,
who lives up the road
and who has a great voice.
La la la.
Yeah.
We've been told
that he speaks good English.
She sells seashells by the seashore.
Aah, don't ask me to do that.
And yeah, all of the research
that Seamus will share,
has been looked over by a conservation
scientist and a climate scientist
to make sure that it's really solid
and that it's of course in line with
the consensus of the scientific community.
And if you're interested to go deeper
into any of this:
Every time we'll share a fact, you'll see
a little orange dot in the corner of the screen.
Somewhere here for you, I guess.
Um.
And it means that you can look up
the source material on The Week's website.
As for us, you’ll see that sometimes
we’ll be reading from a sheet of paper.
Well, that’s exactly for the same reason:
We want to make sure
we get things as right as possible.
Okay.
This being said, today is day one
and it's the hard day.
It's where we go down to U together
and, and face what's coming.
You know, if I have a serious illness,
I want to know exactly where I'm at,
so I can do something about it.
And it's the same with this crisis.
Like in 10 or 20 or 30 years,
I want to be able to say, I have no regrets.
Like I knew what was coming
and I did what I wanted to do.
And, and that's why we created The Week.
We feel that everyone has a right
to look into this
and then to decide for themselves
what they wanna do about this or not.
And if you’re one of the people
who’ve been grappling deeply with this already,
maybe even for years… uh, we invite you
to still go fully into the experience,
and see what might show up for you this time.
[Deep breath] OK.
Let’s jump right in.
[Music]
We’ve come to understand that the reason
most people aren’t terrified
about the environmental crisis
is that we tend to take it in, in pieces.
We see floods in the news
or a catastrophic spill somewhere.
It might be shocking, yes,
but we also have to rush to work.
The next day
we might hear about massive wildfires
and how that will happen more and more often
as the world gets warmer.
But then we also have dinner to fix, right?
And it’s not like we don’t know
what’s happening.
But it never comes together
to make a complete picture.
And it’s hard to see how it has anything
to do with our own lives.
And today we don't want to do that.
Today, we want to lay out all the big pieces
on the table like we do with a puzzle.
And then we'll try to assemble it
so that we can take in the big picture.
And see, you know,
what's actually there.
Seamus, uh, over to you.
The first big piece we will talk about is
how the living world is collapsing
everywhere around the world.
Life is this incredible miracle!
So much beauty that’s been around forever.
We sometimes hear about
one or another species
that is endangered or disappearing.
But most of us don’t realize that it’s
almost every form of life that is declining,
every year a bit more, everywhere on earth.
Let’s look at a few examples.
Take birds.
In the US, a third of all birds
have disappeared in the past 50 years.
With regards to insects,
the most detailed study ever done,
in Germany,
shows that the speed of disappearance
is even faster!
And they are still declining.
You might remember road trips
from your childhood
with the windshield full of insects,
but that’s no longer the case.
Large fish have disappeared
to an even greater degree.
There are only 10% left.
The oceans are almost empty.
Forests?
We lose an area of the size of Italy
every year!
The same decline happens with
wetlands, mangroves, corals and topsoil.
So much has disappeared,
in just one or two generations!
And it continues so fast
that in our lifetime,
if we continue on our current trajectory,
in many places, some of these
could dangerously approach zero.
Here is a piece of data that shows
how much life has already vanished.
Take all the wild mammals that live
everywhere in this beautiful world.
Separately, let’s take all of
us humans and our livestock.
Now let’s imagine we put these two groups
on a scale and compare their weight.
Take a guess:
which group do you think is heavier?
We, humans and our livestock, now represent
96% of the mass of all mammals on earth.
We've overrun everything else.
Wild mammals are down to 4%!
And that’s all that’s left
and they’re still declining.
What we are experiencing right now,
scientists call it a “mass extinction”
event,
the 6th mass extinction on earth.
I remember in high school learning about
the 5 mass extinctions that have happened,
millions of years ago, and,
and wiped out most of life.
It's mind blowing when I read and, and,
and try to grapple with the fact
that I am now,
that we are now in the middle of,
there is no other term for it...
we are in the middle of a mass extinction.
There comes a moment where we push this
so far that it boomerangs back at us.
I don't know if you've played
the game Kerplunk when you were little,
but it's a good way to visualize
how these extinctions relate to us.
In the game, you take turns
taking out a stick.
The goal is to not let the marbles fall.
Imagine for a second
that each marble is a species.
Insects, birds, trees.
Everything that makes up an ecosystem.
One of the marbles is us, humans.
Every time we take over an ecosystem,
clear a forest,
drain a swamp,
create monocultures,
it’s like we pull out a stick.
At first, not much happens.
So we keep going.
But then one marble drops:
a species goes extinct in some place.
Then another.
And another.
Until you take just one more stick,
and suddenly, nearly all the marbles
come crashing down.
Ecosystems behave
in a somewhat similar fashion.
They are remarkably resilient,
until they suddenly collapse.
Here is an example from a place where
we’ve pushed overfishing just a bit too far.
Suddenly this ecosystem collapsed.
And the jellyfish population exploded
and completely took over
and crowded out the remaining fish
and everything else.
We humans tend to think
that we are separate from nature.
But when oceans are empty
and forests are gone,
when there are no insects
to pollinate all our crops,
we human beings
come crashing down with the rest.
We could stop the first episode here and
just deal with this one fact of mass extinction.
And let it sink in.
But unfortunately
there is a lot more happening.
Life collapsing is just one of the three crises
we’ll be talking about today.
The next crisis is pollution.
Since the industrial revolution,
people all over the world
have been exposed to pollution
often without even knowing about it.
But now it's catching up with us.
Frank knows about his first hand.
He lives in Memphis, Tennessee.
In a community that's been devastated
by pollution.
I was a typical child from South Memphis,
you know,
growing up in the late seventies, early eighties.
I was like the first person to have a fade.
So I brought the fade in 1977/78
or whatever this was.
It was really a great time.
But in the midst of that, you started,
we started noticing some
different things happening with mom.
We will get pieces of her saying
and doing crazy things.
And I remember being freaked out
because I had heard the stories of
her mother having cancer.
And a few years later...
My big sister,
brain tumor, cancerous brain tumor,
same part of the brain as my mom's.
And then a few days later,
my mom's only remaining sister.
She's diagnosed with brain cancer too.
So getting back in the neighborhood
and talking to people.
All of us are having the same stories.
Castalia, which is right across from us,
that whole block was taken out from cancer.
Now right here is Hamilton High School.
And they said one time this school
was covered in arsenic.
You can see the towers of the refinery.
They put the refinery on the river
to dump into the river.
And we turn to the right,
there's the Defense Depot.
This is where they stored
the worst of the worst.
All of this is having an effect
in black communities.
Children with the behavior disorders,
uh, neurological disorders, all of this stuff.
And everyone is sitting here
shrugging it off.
What happened to Frank, his family
and his community is devastating.
It’s beyond words.
Pollution is everywhere,
and no one is safe from it.
But so often,
the worst kind of pollution
is concentrated
where working class people
and minorities live.
Every year, in the US,
350,000 people’s lives are cut short
just from air pollution.
And in Europe it’s 417,000.
417,000 deaths!
It's grayish.
Even when it's sunny,
it's overcast and you can see that it's pollution.
I mean, what we see there is what we breathe
in.
It goes inside us, into our lungs.
It's scary, actually.
Pollution is a health risk multiplier.
It increases the risk
of so many different things.
I'm already seeing way more patients
with respiratory problems,
like asthma and chronic obstructive
pulmonary disease, lung diseases.
There is another form of pollution
that’s found everywhere, but even less visible.
Something we didn't know, 50 years ago
when we started producing plastic,
is that the plastic we throw out
or the plastics in the clothes
we might be wearing right now
break down into microplastics.
Tiny, invisible bits
that are carried everywhere.
Literally everywhere.
Researchers have gone to
the most remote place on earth, the Arctic.
And when they melted a gallon of ice,
they found it contains...
Are you ready?
53,000 particles of plastic.
Carried for thousands of miles by the wind.
Microplastic is everywhere,
in the ocean, in the rain, in the rivers.
It's in your tap water.
It's in the bottled water.
It's been found in beer and salt.
It's in the air we're breathing right now.
The air you’re breathing too.
According to researchers
at the University of New Castle in Australia,
in one week, we eat, drink and breathe
the equivalent of one credit card in plastic.
That's 4 a month.
It's even found in the placenta
of pregnant mothers.
And in our bloodstream.
Most likely there are microplastics
in your bloodstream.
What this is doing to our health
we don't yet know.
What we do know is
that industry experts predict
that plastic production won't decrease,
but most likely increase
by a factor of four in the next 30 years.
How much plastic
will end up in our bodies?
And plastic is just one form of pollution.
Meanwhile we've released chemicals,
pesticides, and heavy metals everywhere.
You've probably also read
that our rivers, lakes, and drinking water
are full of medications
like antidepressants and hormones.
We know that this is doing weird things.
Scientists have found that even in
what may look like pristine lakes and rivers
and national wildlife refuges,
the chemicals and medication in the water
disrupt the hormonal systems of wildlife
and turn male fish into half female beings.
They have eggs in their testicles.
It's in the water we humans drink also.
Infant boys are developing more
genital abnormalities and smaller penises.
More girls are experiencing early puberty.
Adult women appear to be suffering
declining egg quality
and significantly more miscarriages.
In men there's a boom in two-headed sperm.
An international team, including researchers
from the school of medicine
of Mount Sinai in New York,
found that in just 40 years,
the human sperm count in Western countries
went down by almost 60%.
Following the current trend,
the team of researchers suggested
sperm count could reach zero in 20 years.
I don't know how this lands with you.
But 20 years, that's exactly about the time
that our children could want
to become parents.
And so for me, this doesn't just feel like,
you know, some science article.
When I look at our children
and I don't know
what's happening in their body,
it feels really personal and,
and disturbing.
So we talked about life collapsing,
about pollution.
And of course, we all know this,
it’s getting warmer.
But before we dive in, let’s start with
a little science refresher on
where the atmosphere is
and why it's getting warmer.
Our planet is surrounded by the atmosphere,
a very thin layer of air.
Incredibly thin,
but absolutely vital.
It’s a blanket that protects us
from freezing.
Without it, heat would simply go back
into outer space.
Gasses in the atmosphere
let the sun rays through,
but trap some of that solar energy.
And that keeps us warm.
The trouble is:
when we burn coal, oil, gas or forests
we release huge quantities of carbon dioxide,
methane, and similar gases into the atmosphere
which makes the blanket
get thicker and thicker.
It's the reason you don't leave
a dog or a kid
in a car alone on a sunny day
with the windows up.
If the sun is shining hard, of course
you leave the windows a bit open!
Otherwise the closed windows trap the heat
and your dog or child might die.
That’ s what’s happening
to the earth right now…
We are closing the windows,
and it’s getting hotter and hotter.
With all the gas we’ve added,
the world has become
1.1° Celsius warmer already.
That’s 2° Fahrenheit.
It doesn’t sound like much,
but it turns out that
the world’s thermostat is
really, really sensitive.
It’s kind of like our body.
When our body temperature increases
by 1° Celsius or 2° Fahrenheit,
you know, we start to have fever.
And maybe you remember
the heat dome of 2021
when it was so hot
that, all the way north in Canada,
a town self-combusted
and burnt down in a day?
Extreme weather events
have always happened.
But now, normal is no longer normal.
Not when a city like Houston, Texas,
has experienced a “five-hundred year flood”...
... three years in a row!
And do you remember these images?
This was San Francisco,
during the day!
This is smoke from the massive fires.
Ashley, the family doctor in California,
was right there.
So I was on maternity leave and
I was nursing her in the breakfast nook.
And the Paradise Fire started.
It was like one of the
historically worst fires in California.
The smoke was terrible.
And I couldn't take her outside
for 13 days.
I was bringing the air purifier
right beside her
and trying to shut the doors of the room.
Trying to keep her safe.
I felt like I was seeing her future
and all of our children's future.
It brought the climate crisis
from that intellectual,
cerebral somewhere else, someone else.
Not my life.
It brought it all home.
And you know, I was like watching it and
just tears falling onto her as I realize,
like I've just been asleep.
[Sirens]
Global warming, doesn't only mean
things get warmer.
It means weather patterns
get out of whack.
We get floods and droughts
that didn't used to exist
for a thousand years.
Droughts all the way up to
Sweden and Canada.
Floods like we've never seen in Germany,
Belgium, the UK and so many other places.
Weather patterns are changing everywhere.
And more and more of us are
experiencing this firsthand.
Polls show that people everywhere,
farmers, city folk, conservatives,
progressives, and moderates
are now concerned or alarmed with
how the climate is changing.
And as we said, in these films,
we are focusing on Europe
and North America.
But if we want to see
what the future holds for us here,
we only need to look to
some parts of the world
where things are already much worse.
Take Malawi, in east Africa.
Because of droughts, floods
and certain farming practices,
farmers’ corn yield per acre
fell from 7 bags to below 3.
The country can no longer
reliably feed itself.
Put yourselves in the shoes of people there.
Malawi contributed almost nothing,
less than 0.1%, a rounding error
to the warming blanket,
but they are hit really hard.
Or take Syria and its brutal civil war.
It started in 2011, after the country suffered
the worst 5-year drought in its history.
One and a half million farmers
had to give up their land
and move to overcrowded cities
and find a way to scrape by.
These droughts were devastating.
And many analysts believe
they were a critical factor
in sparking the mass protests
that Syria’s dictator then ruthlessly suppressed,
leading to the terrible civil war.
6 million people had to flee their homes
to neighboring countries.
And one million found refuge in Europe.
What the people in Malawi and Syria
have been through
might just be
what we'll face in the future too.
OK, let’s, um, let's pause for a second
and, and do a quick time out.
I don’t know how this all lands with you.
You know, this can be pretty hard
or even overwhelming.
And, and maybe for some of you it's,
it's not like...
I've, I've noticed that, you know,
sometimes to protect myself from bad news,
there are some protection mechanism
that seem to pop up.
You know, kind of unconsciously,
it's like my brain is trying to protect me.
And over time we've noticed
that it comes
in a number of different shapes.
And we wanted to share that with you.
A first mechanism that I noticed a lot is,
is that we might tune out.
Maybe you've looked at your phone,
earlier during this film.
I know that I do that a lot,
just to zone out for a second.
Number two is denial.
Maybe during this film
you've been thinking:
It can't be this bad.Or:
what do these people know?
Number three is:
I already know this.
There's nothing new for me to hear.
No need for me
to engage with this again.
Or four: Wishful thinking.
Maybe you've been thinking:
Well, someone will come up with some
technology that will make things okay.
Or five: This won’t affect me.
I'll be okay, this is a problem
for other people.
I'm in a safe place.
Or I'm resourceful enough.
Or six, uh: Jumping to solutions.
If only people did this or that.
Or I'm already doing this and
I'm already doing that.
So I'm doing my part and
I can stop thinking about it.
Look at the list
and see if one or several
have happened to you
during the film so far.
If you're like me, like...
it will have happened, right?
It's okay.
And, it's actually, it's normal.
It's normal to be heartbroken
or fearful or, or angry.
Something like heartbreaks, you know,
serves a really important purpose.
It reveals to us what we care about,
you know, what is precious to us.
So precious that it hurts and that,
that we feel moved to do something about it.
And so here's my invitation to you.
Tf you catch this happening again,
it's okay.
Just try to go back and,
and focus on the film again.
OK, so, let’s go back!
The planet is getting hotter and
the weather increasingly out of whack.
And when we started reading up on this,
we read about what scientists predict
will happen at some point in the future.
Say in 2050.
And to be honest, at first, 2050,
it sounded quite far away.
Until one day, we simply calculated
how old we’ll be in 2050,
and how old our children will be.
And to us that was like a real shock.
Because we realized like, hey, in 2050,
you know, we'll be in our mid seventies.
So hopefully we'll still be around
and healthy and happy and
and happily retired.
And we realized that our kids
will be in their thirties.
They'll be younger than we are today.
And, you know, we don't feel that old.
Right, and suddenly everything that
we are reading about the world in 2050,
no longer felt abstract.
You know, it, really hit home.
So now we often ask our friends
to do the same calculation.
In 2050, I would be 69.
I will be 56.
I will be 57 years old in 2050.
In thirty years, I'll be almost 90.
If I'm still 90 by then.
So how about you?
How old will you be in 2050?
Just take your age
and add roughly 25 or 30 years.
Now think of a child in your life
you care about.
Your own child or a niece or a nephew,
or, you know, a child
that's important to you.
[Frank] I think about my nephews.
[Ashley] My daughter.
[Holly and John] My children.
[Ophélie] I think of Lency, my niece.
[Yancy] My great grandchildren.
Who are you thinking of?
If you are all in the same room,
we invite you to say their name aloud
to the other people in your group.
Yeah, like, seriously,
say their name out loud.
Even if it feels weird at first,
or if you're all speaking at the same time,
or if no one dares to start.
There is something powerful
in saying their name out loud.
[Music]
Now add 25 or 30 years to their age too
and say that number out aloud as well.
In 2050, Calla will be 32.
I might be a parent
of children in their twenties.
So Noah is 43 and Zia is 40, right?
When I'm 90 years old,
my children will be 42 and 45.
I think of Lency, my niece.
She will be 34 years old.
At that age, what's the kind of life
you would want them to have?
You know, in a normal world, right?
If, if there wasn't any mass extinction
or pollution or warming.
[Yancy] I want my grandson’s life
to be relaxed.
Stress free.
[John] I see my children
sweet and healthy and happy.
[Ashley] She’ll probably have a career,
maybe, of some kind.
She will be kind of establishing herself
I would think.
I might have encouraged
my children
to study innovation
or of course, whatever they like.
I wish that for everyone,
not only for my future children.
I hope children
will grow up in a normal world.
I would like to be in good health,
to be happy,
at the end of my professional career.
[Peter] That my family has grown,
that my children,
that they have children of their own
and to be there with a large family
and I would be a part of that family.
If that came true, I would say,
that this life has been worth it.
[Yancy] Hummingbird's flying by,
sitting out on the porch with my grandson,
just sharing stories
and just looking forward to getting up
every morning.
In 2050, I would like to be
a trauma surgeon.
I would have liked to have met Taylor Swift
who is my favorite singer.
I would be her backing singer any day.
You know, at nighttime, we can sit up
and, you know, just dream on the stars.
Let our imaginations go and create,
you know,
and do all of these wonderful things
that I think that we were meant to do.
These are the kinds of things
we might all wish for ourselves.
But unless we massively turn the ship around,
2050 is not going to look like this at all.
All the fires and wars and refugees
we talked about earlier
are just the beginning.
Because we've been adding so much
warming gas to the blanket
in the last few years,
the world is now getting hotter,
really fast.
A group of scientists in Switzerland
found a clever way for us
to get a sense of how quickly
things will change.
They published a study
where they project,
for all large cities around the world,
what the weather will be like in thirty years.
For example, what kind of climate will
Montreal and Toronto have, in 2050?
It’ll be pretty much like
Washington D.C is today.
That’s the closest match
the group of scientists found.
No more snow,
but mosquitos.
Boston?
It will be like
Charlotte, North Carolina, today.
Chicago will be like Kansas City.
And Kansas City will be like Dallas.
Portland, Oregon will move South
all the way to San Antonio.
For San Diego the closest match is
Tripoli in Libya.
Austin, Texas: Peshawar, Pakistan.
Los Angeles: Hargeisa in Somalia.
In Europe, Helsinki and Tallinn will move
1600 kilometers south to Bratislava.
Paris will move to Istanbul.
Rome? To Izmir, in Turkey!
And Madrid? The closest match is Tehran in Iran.
It’s as if the whole of Europe and the US
moves hundreds of miles.
And some bits drift off,
in less than 30 years!
Think about where you live.
And what makes it feel
like “home” for you.
You know, whatever feels like home
will change.
Maybe you are into hiking,
or hunting, or fishing, or skiing.
Well, the kind of trees, and fish
and animals you are used to
are likely to change dramatically
when your home moves
hundreds of miles down the map.
The kind of farming and economy
might not be the same.
Cities will become much hotter,
sometimes too hot to enjoy city life.
Whatever you call home
is going to change...a lot.
So, life collapsing, pollution, warming…
We are all going to be affected
in some way.
We can't predict exactly
when and how things will hit us.
You know, scientists have
really powerful models,
but they don't have a crystal ball.
But we do have a pretty good sense
of what is most likely to hit us.
It's migration and
food shortages.
Let's start with the first one,
with migration.
There are lots of places where we live
that might not have a future.
If you live there,
you will have to move.
Say you live in an area that’s affected,
more and more often,
by repeat fires, droughts,
floods or hurricanes.
There comes a point
where insurance companies calculate
that the risk has become too high
and they pull out
and stop offering coverage.
Banks stop making mortgage loans
Which means no more house buyers,
and house prices collapse.
A few people see it coming,
and are lucky to sell just in time.
Most others will see the equity
they built up suddenly wiped out.
The community shrinks,
there are less taxes to support it,
and the school system
and civic services falter,
pushing more people to leave.
Everyone will be affected.
But whoever can’t afford to leave,
usually the elderly
and working class people,
will stay behind and suffer most.
And perhaps this sounds extreme,
but it's already starting to happen.
For example, after hurricane Andrew
insurance companies pulled out
of many places in Florida.
Those communities would have collapsed!
The Florida Legislature created
a state-run insurance scheme
forced to offer coverage for places
that no private insurer will touch anymore.
But the climate risk hasn’t disappeared.
In no time, it’s Florida’s taxpayers
who took on a massive insurance risk:
$511 billion.
More than seven times
the state’s total budget.
That risk can’t be sustainable.
It’s not just Florida
where the writing is on the wall
for some communities.
There are places throughout the US
where people start to realize
that their town might not make it.
In North and South Carolina,
in Louisiana,
in New Mexico,
California,
Alaska.
Across the Atlantic, in the UK,
the town of Fairbourne
is already a step further.
It’s not just a hypothetical situation.
It’s officially being decommissioned.
It’s like pronouncing a death sentence
on a community.
Sea levels are rising,
and building a seawall
to protect Fairbourne from floods
is too costly.
Not everything can be saved,
and the government is abandoning
Fairborne to the elements.
People who live there will be forced
to leave by 2054 at the latest.
Banks no longer give mortgages
and house prices have collapsed.
There are currently no plans
to compensate homeowners
whose asset value was wiped out.
Local and national governments
will have to make more and more
of these heartbreaking calls,
which places get saved through sea walls,
flood protection and water pipes,
and which won't.
And when decision makers rule
that a place is not worth saving,
will people - like you and I -
will we go quietly?
Or will we fight with everything we have?
It’s not just sea level rise
like in Fairbourne.
People will have to move away from places
that become too hot to live comfortably.
Remember the heatwave of 2003 in Europe
that caused 70,000 deaths?
It was the hottest year on record
in 500 years.
By 2040, that will be
an average summer.
In 2050, scientists believe
almost every summer will be hotter,
and some much hotter.
Banks and financial investors
obviously watch this closely.
They buy expensive reports to determine
where it's becoming too risky to invest.
We were able to put our hands
on some of the maps and those reports,
prepared by a firm called Moody's.
When it comes to hurricanes,
these are the places deemed at high risk.
This is where you might
find yourself stranded,
if insurance companies, banks
and investors pull out.
Here are the communities
Moody’s warns investors about,
because they’ll experience
severe water stress.
When water gets scarce,
people leave.
These are the places
where communities might not have a future
because of recurring wildfires.
Here are the communities
where the heat stress in the summer
will be so intense
that working outside becomes impossible
during the day,
which brings down the local economy.
And then there’s extreme rainfalls.
And rising sea levels.
Do you, or do any of your friends
or anyone in your group
live in one of those places?
[Music]
Investors worry about their money,
but for each of us
who live in these places,
we've got much more at stake.
We are busy building up our lives,
in communities,
and all the while a storm is brewing
that might destroy it all
and knock us back to zero.
The US military has done
a similar assessment.
This map shows the military bases
inside the US they are worried
will suffer from floods, heat stress,
fires or sea levels rising.
It’s all over the place.
We’ve put the maps you’ve just seen
on The Week’s website.
So after this episode,
you can look up what they say.
So, in 2050, there is a serious risk
that either you’ll have moved
or live in a place
people are moving away from.
Or as in our case in upstate NY,
that you live in a place
where lots of people will want to move to.
This animation is based on
important work
published in the “Proceedings of the
National Academy of Sciences”.
The red zones on this map show the places
that are unlivable hot zones today.
It’s 1% of the world’s surface.
In 2050, these are the areas
projected to become so hot
that life is almost impossible.
And 20 years later it’s even worse.
“Global warming” doesn’t really
capture this.
It’s more like “global scorching”.
Estimates for climate refugees
worldwide in 2050,
that’s less than 30 years from now,
range from 200 million to 1 billion.
Some of Central America and large parts
of Africa will be unlivable hot zones
and millions will do whatever it takes
to make it to the US and Europe to survive.
Climate migration is already happening
Not long ago,
9,000 climate refugees from Honduras
fled north following Hurricane Eta.
They were turned back with clubs and
tear gas at the Guatemalan border.
Every year, 1,000 to 5,000 migrants die,
trying to reach Europe.
What will happen as this intensifies?
Will we let refugees die
on the other side of the border?
Will Canada erect a border wall to keep
people from the US from moving north?
Will Northern Scandinavia turn back boats
from mainland Europe?
That's 2050
when it comes to migration.
It's not that far away.
Just remember how old you'll be
or the child that you thought about in 2050,
when they will experience this.
Okay. It's time to move to our next topic.
Food.
[Music]
There are 7.9 billion people
on earth right now.
And there might be close to
10 billion of us in 2050.
How are we going to feed all of us?
There are 6 major breadbaskets
in the world.
Each one of them will face major issues.
For example, in the
Midwestern United States,
extreme heat waves, droughts and floods
could cause large-scale crop failures.
Not to mention that this bread basket
sits squarely on the Ogallala aquifer,
the biggest in the United States,
and it is being pumped dry.
Already, California faces
massive water shortages,
because the snowpack
in the Sierra Nevada Mountains
no longer feeds the rivers reliably
and the aquifers there too are running dry.
No water, no food.
Every one of the 6 major bread baskets
faces new risks.
And by 2050, researchers believe
that 1 year out of 3,
two breadbaskets or more
will fail at the same time,
leading to hunger and social unrest.
The risks on the food system
are piling on,
just when we need to find a way
to feed 2 more billion people.
It’s hard also to imagine
how we’ll avoid terrible wars.
Just take this one case:
India and Pakistan will be parched.
In red again here the zones so hot
it will be almost unlivable.
India and Pakistan, that's 2 billion people
with nowhere to go.
Trapped between the Himalayas
and the Indian Ocean.
You know, in two countries
who are already have
tense military relationships.
They both have nuclear weapons.
And so do seven other countries
in the world.
Closer to home,
it sometimes feels like our democracies
are already hanging on by a thread.
And I really do worry,
can they last for another 30 years?
When there’ll be millions of
internal and external refugees
and tensions rise to a whole new level?
When some towns get saved
with expensive infrastructure
and others not.
And when there’ll be food shortages.
Will there be riots and violence?
These are all legitimate questions!
And perhaps you think
that we shouldn’t worry.
But the fact
that we are even discussing this,
discussing if these dominoes will fall
or if they will stand...
That in itself feels crazy to me!
And we know this is
a lot of information to take in.
You know, if you,
if you need to stretch for a second,
or move around,
feel free to do so.
Because,
if this wasn’t bad enough there is
one more thing we need to talk about,
that could make everything
a whole lot worse.
The big thing that scientists worry about
are what they call tipping points.
If the warming passes
certain thresholds,
it sets off chain reactions
that speed up the warming even more.
Each one of those tipping points
is like a booby trap
that can’t be stopped,
once it’s set off.
For example, by 2050,
the Amazon rainforest,
because so much of it has been cut back,
might reach the point
where the water cycle changes
and the remaining forest dries out,
burns, and turns into a savannah.
We’ll lose the most magnificent ecosystem
in the world
and with it the indigenous communities
with their ancestral traditions and wisdom.
And the smoke of half a continent will add
a whole new layer to the atmosphere.
In Alaska, Russia and Canada,
the permafrost,
the ground that is permanently frozen,
starts to thaw
and it releases huge amounts of methane
into the atmosphere.
A gas that traps eighty times more heat
than carbon dioxide.
If we hit these tipping points,
things spiral out of control
and we land in what scientists call
a “hothouse” scenario
where climate systems shift
to something entirely new
and civilization as we know it
is likely to collapse.
These tipping points are
one of the reasons
the United Nations and others say
we MUST keep warming below 2° Celsius,
and preferably below 1.5°.
Here is the crazy thing:
if we don’t significantly change course,
we might see a rise in temperature
of 2° Celsius by 2050.
And that’s when some of the booby traps
might go off.
That’s in my lifetime!
And, you know,
people who are totally freaking out
about climate change?
Well, they are doing so
because of this!
I wonder how this all
lands with you.
Clearly for us it, you know, changed
the whole way we think about our future.
We had to grieve
the normal future
that we thought
that we’d have.
And everyone we know
who grapples deeply with this
seems to go through this
in their own way.
[Music]
[Frank] We're facing
extinction level events around here.
We're looking at environmental collapse.
It scares me for my nephews.
You know, my oldest nephew is 24.
My youngest one is 19.
And that can probably be
one of the main
why I don't have kids now.
[Holly] Like even when I hear the question,
do I want grandkids?
It's like, of course I want grandkids.
And at the same time,
it feels like a little electric shock
at my heart.
Because right now I don’t see
things changing fast enough.
Like if it's my kids
and they're having kids
and there are these awful things
that have gotten worse,
I need to be able to say,
I tried to do my best,
cause it does wake me up
in the middle of the night.
I love life.
And I don't want to tell myself
that when I'm 56,
my life may be potentially over,
because we didn't take care of
this freaking planet.
And today,
I want to live
and I want to enjoy life.
And I want the people around me
to be able to do so too.
The truth is, we can no longer
plan 20 years ahead.
It doesn't make sense to work out
strategies when things are so uncertain.
We kind of have to unlearn planning
far into the future,
it's a painful part of the grieving process.
I’m brown, so I’m from Kashmir as well,
not just the Netherlands.
And I know that, like, I can’t visit
where my ancestor’s came from
because that has been destroyed
by flooding.
Um, that’s kinda something
I’ve always grown up with knowing.
But then I'm very scared,
how my children will be able
to live then.
Well, I don't know,
what will happen to them,
when there is not enough food,
when there is not enough water anymore,
when there is no housing that is liveable.
That is the scenario that we face.
[Ashely] Will our kids have the chance
to make the choice to be parents
Will it be, like, possible
to want to have a kid in 20, or 30 years?
I don't know.
And it, like, makes me feel so sad
and guilty for my generation.
That we could be robbing
all of the humans to come
from making that choice.
Like if we love our kids,
we need to be revolting.
We need to change everything.
And we're not.
I used to picture my future,
when I’m older,
with some of the things
that my parents love in their life today.
They are retired,
they cook good food,
they love gardening,
they love spending time
with their grandkids.
And that’s what I would like
for us too of course.
But I’ve come to accept
that’s not what’s going to happen.
Most likely,
unless we radically turn things around.
When I’m old, when we’re old, um,
it won’t be a happy retirement.
But most likely the hardest years
of our lives.
We know that Raphael and Noemie,
our children,
will most likely face real suffering,
probably hunger and violence
in our lifetime,
and after we die,
we are no longer around to protect them.
You know, this is my daughter,
Noemie.
The thing that breaks my heart,
over and over again,
is when Raphael or Noemie
come up all excited
and share something
about when they will have children.
You know, "Daddy, Daddy,
this, this picture book, you know,
can I keep it for my children?"
And, and I try to smile and I, I say “Yes!”
and, and inside my heart breaks
because I know that you'll want to have
children around 2040 or 2050.
And, you know,
unless we massively change course,
I don't know
if you'll want to have children by then.
But I don't say this and I, I smile and...
because I feel like they still have a right
to some innocence.
Like, you know, it's,
it's too early to tell them.
This is it for today.
And part of you might feel relieved
that we addressed this topic head on.
Or perhaps you’re just glad
it's finally over.
And maybe none of this comes
as a surprise to you.
Or perhaps you feel numb.
Or you’re feeling anger,
or shock, or sadness.
Or disbelief.
Or all of the above.
And maybe what’s most present for you
is one of the protection mechanisms
we talked about earlier.
Like “I already knew all this.”
Or “It can’t be this bad."
Or, “I’m already doing my part,
so I don’t need to think about this”.
Whatever you feel,
in our experience, it’s okay.
You know, this,
this “U” that we talked about earlier
looks a little different for everyone.
And, in a minute, when the film is over,
we’ll invite you to have a conversation
about this with your group.
We have prepared
a little conversation starter
you can use to kick things off.
And after the conversation,
when you go back to your life,
we have this suggestion for you:
try to stay with whatever you’re feeling,
even or especially if it’s uncomfortable.
And try not to numb yourself
or throw yourself into the next activity.
Stay with it, soak it in.
T he sadness, the anger we can feel
is important.
It's normal
and it serves an important purpose.
Because in our experience,
the more we allow ourselves to feel this,
the more energy will come up
at some point in us
to do something about this.
And I know it can be tempting
to suppress those feelings.
But then we're also cutting ourselves off
from the energy that they might give us.
That being said, um,
if you feel really anxious
and you need support,
please ask for help.
Talk to a friend!
We have also put
some resources for you online.
There’s a button that says, um,
“I need support”, click on it.
Don’t keep this to yourself
if you feel overwhelmed.
Remember:
why do we choose to go through this?
Because we have a right to know.
Right, everyone has a right to know.
And then we have a right to decide
what we wanna do about it,
so that
if we choose to do so,
we can say
I have no regrets.
And, just so you know:
Today was the hardest part.
S tay with us for parts 2 and 3.
Frankly, this would be
the worst time to stop!
And the next time is all going to be
about the big question:
So now what?
Is there still hope?
We'll zoom out and try to understand:
How did we get into this mess?
And is there a way out?
Because we've got to fix this, you know.
After all there is no place else for us to
go.
So, see you soon
for episode 2,
and before that, in a minute,
to kick off your group conversation.